Department of Marine Sciences University of Gothenburg # +46 704 19 47 01 Website: mtomasini.github.io Citizenship: Switzerland Birthdate: 1989-11-21



Matteo Tomasini

Summary

I am an enthusiast scientist, active for years in the theoretical realm of evolutionary biology. My main interest is the development of computational tools and data analysis pipelines to study problems of various nature. I have a keen eye for using the right methods for each problem at hand. My toolbox is particularly well suited for agent-based simulations and mathematical modelling, as well as statistical analysis and machine learning. In the years I also learned how to best apply best practices to programming, in order to write stable and maintainable code.

Skills

Simulations, programming, (Python, R, C++, Matlab), I developed various population- and individual-based simulations to address questions in population genetics and climatology.

Statistical analysis, (Python, R, Stan), I performed statistical analysis on simulations outputs and datasets using different methodologies, including Bayesian inference and machine learning. I further worked towards the development of a statistical method to extract information from genomic datasets. I also taught applied biostatistics to master students.

Mathematical and numerical modelling, (Wolfram Mathematica), I worked on several mathematical models to study selected questions in population genetics and climatology.

Scientific writing, (LATEX, Word), I wrote several papers exposing the research results from my team, and published them in international peer-reviewed journals.

Scientific dissemination, I contributed during 10 years to the growth of one of the largest Facebook pages about popular science in Italian.

Experience

Research

Mar 2021 – Present **Postdoctoral research fellow**, Department of Marine Sciences, Göteborgs Universitet, Sweden.

> I modelled evolutionary mechanisms leading to the establishment of species' distributions in the Baltic Sea, using Python, C++ and Matlab.

Sep 2019 - Dec 2020 Postdoctoral research associate, Department of Integrative Biology, Michigan State University, United States of America.

> I worked on developing a Bayesian statistical method to harness genetic information for the inference of the demographic history of a species.

Feb 2015 – Jun 2019 PhD student, Interfaculty Bioinformatics Unit, Universität Bern, Switzerland. I developed mathematical models and simulations in Python to study the rapid adaptation of species at risk of extinction in a spatially structured model.

Teaching

Sep 2017 – Jun 2019 **Substitute lecturer**, Applied Biostatistics I and II, Universität Bern. Substitution of main lecturer in case of absence.

Sep 2015 – Jun 2019 **Teaching assistant**, Applied Biostatistics I and II, Universität Bern.

Management of exercise sessions and support for MSc students, correction of exercise sheets

Sep 2015, 2016, 2017 **Teaching assistant**, *Introduction to R*, Universität Bern.

and 2018 Teaching assistant during a 5 days introductory course to the R language.

Education

Feb 2015 – Jun 2019 **PhD studies in ecology & evolution**, *Universität Bern, Switzerland*, Supervisors: Dr. S. Peischl and Prof. L. Excoffier.

Relevant courses and workshops: best practices in programming, introduction to Markov models, machine learning. Thesis topic: theoretical population genetics.

Sep 2012 – Oct 2014 **MSc in physics (orientation theoretical physics)**, *Université de Genève, Switzerland.*

Thesis topic: theoretical climatology.

Sep 2009 – Aug 2012 BSc in physics, Université de Genève, Switzerland.

Sep 2004 – Jun 2008 Swiss Matura (classical curriculum), Liceo di Locarno, Switzerland.

Relevant courses: ancient Greek, Latin.

Academic achievments and activities

Peer-reviewed publications

- 3. **M. Tomasini**, S. Peischl, (2022), *The role of spatial structure in multi-deme models of evolutionary rescue*, Journal of Evolutionary Biology, 35(7), 986 1001
- 2. **M. Tomasini**, S. Peischl, (2020), *When does gene flow facilitate evolutionary rescue?*, Evolution, 74(8), 1640 1653
- 1. **M. Tomasini**, S. Peischl, (2018), *Establishment of locally adapted mutations under divergent selection*, Genetics, 209(3), 885 895

Submitted for publication

1a. **M. Tomasini**, M. Eriksson, K. Johannesson, M. Rafajlović (2022), *Species' ranges and the steepening-gradient hypothesis*, bioRxiv, https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.03.19.484973

Grants

750€ International Council for the Exploration of the Sea (ICES) Early Career Scientist funding, Baltic Sea Science Congress 2021

Rejected with Seal of *The evolution of marine species in continuous space*, Marie Skłodowska-Curie Excellence Actions – Individual Fellowship 2020, Evaluation Score: 90.40%

Selected oral contributions

- Oct 2022 Fight or flight? The role of adaptation in shaping future species' distributions in light of climate change (featured session, accepted), YOUMARES 13, Berlin, Germany
- Aug 2022 How do species ranges respond to the effects of counteracting environmental gradients? (accepted), European Society for Evolutionary Biology Congress 2022, Prague, Czech Republic
- Oct 2021 Range expansions along multiple environmental gradients, Baltic Sea Science Congress 2021, Aarhus, Denmark
- Jun 2019 Effects of gene flow and fragmentation on evolutionary rescue, Modelling Ecology & Evolution Zurich 2019, Zurich, Switzerland

Committees

Oct 2021 – present Steering committee, Linnaeus Centre for Marine Evolutionary Biology, University of

Gothenburg

Memberships

May 2022 – present Nordic Research Software Engineers association

Apr 2021 – present Linnaeus Centre for Marine Evolutionary Biology, University of Gothenburg

Mar 2015 - Jul 2019 Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics

Unpaid research experience

Sep 2013 – Oct 2014 MSc thesis, Effect of snow covering and ocean mixed layer on the irreversibility

of sea ice retreat, Institut des Sciences de l'Environnement, Université de Genève,

Supervisors: Dr. M. Brunetti and Dr. S. Marshall.

Feb 2012 BSc short thesis, Measures of polarization of the solar light around the Balmer

Jump, Istituto Ricerche Solari Locarno and Université de Genève, Supervisors:

Dr. M. Bianda and Dr. M. Audard.

References

Current postdoc Prof. Marina Rafajlović marina.rafajlovic@marine.gu.se

supervisor

Postdoc supervisor Prof. Gideon Bradburd bradburd bradburd@msu.edu

PhD supervisor Dr. Stephan Peischl stephan.peischl@bioinformatics.unibe.ch

Miscellaneous

Languages

written / spoken Italian Native language

written / spoken French Full professional working proficiency

written / spoken English Full professional working proficiency

spoken German Limited working proficiency

written / spoken Swedish Base proficiency (Nationella prov i SFI, kurs C)

Other activities

Mar 2012 – Mar 2022 **Co-admin**, *Meccanica Quantistica: gruppo serio*.

Co-administrator and moderator of the largest Facebook page of quantum physics dissemi-

nation in Italian language (\sim 34'000 subscribers).

Aug 2009 – Apr 2019 Battery Sergeant Major, Swiss Armed Forces.

I was responsible for logistics in an artillery battery – in particular personnel, equipment, ammunition, health service and barracks administration – during the yearly one month

service.

Nov 2015 - Jun 2018 Head of refereeing, Swiss Tchoukball.

Head of the refereeing commission and member of the executive committee of the Swiss federation of tchoukball; I developed refereeing in the sport as well as worked on referees'

formation.